

GRADUATE STUDENT · APPLIED MATH

□ 214-404-2591 | ■ tuma.andrew@gmail.com | □ andrewtuma | □ andytuma

Summary_

Current Master's student interested in numerical relativity and gravitational wave detection, actively researching deep learning for understanding and predicting the behavior of chaotic systems. I have experience in machine learning, numerical optimization, computational ODEs/PDEs, data science, and computational physics. I am passionate about public outreach and STEM education.

Education

San Diego State University

San Diego, CA

M.S. IN APPLIED MATH Aug. 2020 - May. 2022

Thesis: Deep Learning Assisted Hankel Dynamic Mode Decomposition

University of Virginia

Charlottesville, VA

B.S. IN PHYSICS

Aug. 2017 - May. 2020

Distinguished Major
 Westmont College

Montecito, CA

B.S. IN PHYSICS (TRANSFERRED)

Aug. 2016 - May. 2017

· Presidential Scholar

Work Experience

Medarcus Los Angeles, CA

DATA SCIENTIST Apr. 2021 - July 2021

- Implemented a new probabilistic patient match algorithm, enabling parallelized computations for record linkage and deduplication.
- · Delivered critical changes to previous codebase on short notice by leveraging POSTMAN, Docker, and Flask.
- Helped design a natural language processing machine to identify patient data more effectively using convolutional neural networks and word
 embedding techniques.

University of Virginia Charlottesville, VA

OBSERVATORY COORDINATOR

Aug. 2018 - Mar. 2020

- Integrated the latest astrophysical news along with Q&A into our biweekly program for public viewings at the historic Leander McCormick Observatory.
- Operated and maintained the modernized 26-inch astrometric refractor telescope originally built in the 1880s.
- Taught guests how to properly use the 14-inch Celestron CGEM DX Schmidt-Cassegrain telescope along with the 6-inch brass Alvin Clark refractor.

Westmont College

Montecito, CA

OBSERVATORY COORDINATOR

Sep. 2016 - May 2017

- Operated the 16-inch and 24-inch research grade reflecting telescopes along with their component software MIRA AL to study and introduce different objects of the night sky to the public.
- Prepared lectures and interactive activities to engage the public and used social media to advertise the events, frequently resulting in record attendance.
- Worked in conjunction with the Santa Barbara Astronomical Unit (SBAU) to spark scientific curiosity through educational gatherings and presentations.

Research

Machine Learning for Nonlinear Dynamics

San Diego State University

Andrew Tuma, Chris Curtis

May. 2021 - Present

· Leverage deep autoencoder networks and times series embedding techniques to predict nonlinear and chaotic dynamics.

Techniques in Spacetime Visualization

University of Virginia

ANDREW TUMA, DAVID NICHOLS

Aug. 2019 - June 2020

• Utilized Python and Matplotlib visualization tools to design a new method for plotting tensor fields which intuitively represent eigenvector/eigenvalue information to fully describe gravitational wave emitting spacetimes.

Pulsed Nuclear Magnetic Resonance

University of Virginia

Andrew Tuma, Bellave Shivaram

Jan. 2019 - April 2019

 Examined the physical properties of several different hydrogen and fluorine nuclei by recording spin-lattice relaxation time, spin echoes, and free induction decay. **Pulsating Variable Stars** Westmont College

Andrew Tuma, Tom Whittemore

Feb. 2017 - June 2017

• Used MIRA AL software and the Westmont Observatory 24-inch reflector telescope to capture data on several different Delta-Scuti pulsating variable stars and then plotted the light curves to obtain information about the properties of the star IP Virginis.

Skills

Programming Python, C/C++, MATLAB, ROOT, LaTex, Github, POSTMAN, Docker

Languages English, Conversational Spanish and German

Presentation

UVA Gravity Group Charlottesville, VA

NEW METHODS IN SPACETIME VISUALIZATION

Introduced new methods of visualizing complex tensor fields representing gravitational wave emitting spacetimes using Python and Matplotlib.

Extracurricular Activity _____

Gravity Group Charlottesville, VA

MEMBER

Aug. 2019 - Aug 2020

- Presented and engaged in current research projects in gravitational physics.
- Attended weekly journal club readings to stay up-to-date on recently published research papers.

Society of Physics Students

University of Virginia

- Aug. 2017 May. 2020 MEMBER • Mentored and tutored younger students within the community in math and science.
- Participated in group GRE help sessions and undergraduate research meetings.

Teaching

2021	Lead Graduate Teaching Assistant , Math 141 - Pre-calculus	San Diego State
2017	Lab Assistant, Introduction to Physics Lab I & II	Westmont College
2017	Teaching Assistant, Introduction to Physics II	Westmont College
2016	Teaching Assistant , Introduction to Physics I	Westmont College

Honors & Awards

2020	Dean's List , University of Virginia	Charlottesville, VA
2017	Dean's List, Westmont College	Montecito, CA
2016	Presidential Scholarship, Westmont College	Montecito, CA
2016	CoServ Electric Scholarship, LEF Scholarship Ceremony	The Colony, TX
2016	TCHS Track Booster Club Scholarship, LEF Scholarship Ceremony	The Colony, TX

Coursework.

- Computational Physics
- Theoretical Astrophysics
- General Relativity
- Computational PDEs
- Computational Fluid Dynamics Numerical Optimization
- Mathematical Physics
- Dynamical Systems and Chaos
- Partial Differential Equations